Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's daf דף daf is kuf
chaf ק"ף kuf chaf 120 and we pick up three lines down
in the wide lines on kuf chaf ק"ף. kuf chaf. The Gemara
גמרא Gemara is in the middle of a somewhat aggadic section where
we're discussing the ways in which Bnot Tzelofchad בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelofchad
approached Moshe משה Moshe and Aharon אהרן, Aharon,
and also then have a little bit of a digression to talk
about the famous aggadata אגדתא aggadata about Yocheved יוכבד. Yocheved. Yocheved יוכבד
Yocheved giving birth, she was born right when the sons of Yaakov
יעקב Yaakov entered Mitzrayim מצרים, Mitzrayim, and she was
130 when
Moshe משה Moshe when she gave birth to Moshe משה. Moshe. The
whole famous story about Amram עמרם Amram separating from her and then
through the prophecy of Miriam מרים Miriam remarrying her and so on.
So again, sort of talking once again what's interesting to note there
in addition, the reason the Gemara גמרא Gemara brought that in
was talking about the age of Bnot Tzelofchad בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelofchad
and how old were they and having children and so on. But
also once again we have a woman Miriam מרים Miriam with her
prophecy and sort of ultimately leading to the birth of Moshe משה
Moshe and knowing more than her father Amram עמרם Amram did in
terms of what the right course of action is. Interesting parallel with
Bnot Tzelofchad בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelofchad and Moshe משה, Moshe, Miriam מרים
Miriam and Amram עמרם Amram and so on. Anyway, the Gemara גמרא
Gemara now continues. L'halan
להלן l'halan three lines down, three lines in the wide lines kuf
chaf ק"ף kuf chaf end of the line. L'halan להלן l'halan later
on, maan hacha ketiv derech gedulatan מן הכא כתיב דרך גדולתן maan
hacha kasiv derech gedulatan when in the order of their birth when
it says at the end of Bemidbar במדבר Bemidbar where it says
that the uncles came and complained and whatever, and then it
says so they married their cousins, their uncles' sons.
And there in that part of the story, the epilogue to the
story,
it lists them in order, it's one listing of them in terms
of the order, whereas when they approached Moshe משה Moshe the names
are given in a different order. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara is
trying to explain why in one order in one place and in
another order the other place. So it says over there
it lists them in the order of their birth of the order
of their age, maan hacha ketiv derech gedulatan מן הכא כתיב דרך
גדולתן. maan hacha kasiv derech gedulatan. V'kan וכאן v'kan and in the
case where they approach Moshe משה Moshe derech chachmatan דרך חכמתן derech
chachmatan in the order of their
wisdom presumably. And this is just based on context when they approached
Moshe משה Moshe and they're coming with their claim,
so presumably it is the Gemara גמרא Gemara before said chachmaniyot hen
חכמניות הן, chachmaniyot hen, they were very
wise. Presumably it's the smartest one who is the one that maybe
more had the idea and so on. Anyway, they're in the middle
of a type of an intellectual debate or discourse, so you're going
to emphasize the smarter one first. Later where it speaks about them
getting married, the older ones are going to get married before the
younger ones, so it mentions the older ones first. That's how the
Gemara גמרא Gemara resolves that.
And the Gemara גמרא Gemara then derives from this mesayei lei l'Rabbi
Ammi מסייע ליה לרבי אמי. mesayei lei l'Rabbi Ammi. This supports Rabbi
Ammi רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi d'amar Rabbi Ammi דאמר רבי אמי, d'amar
Rabbi Ammi, b'yeshiva בישיבה b'yeshiva halach achar chachma הלך אחר חכמה. halach
achar chachma. If you are having a yeshiva ישיבה, yeshiva, here does
not mean a study hall, but it's a similar, it means that
people are sitting for some type of a intellectual discourse or debate
or whatever, then you give respect first
to the wisest one in terms of who you're going to sit
at the head of the table. Other forms you show deference to
the one who is the wisest. B'mesiba במסיבה b'mesiba if you are
having just a meal,
it's not about an issue of intellectual, you talk at the meal
but you more shmooze or whatever, it's not about fundamentally an intellectual
type of an issue, so there halach achar zikna הלך אחר זקנה,
halach achar zikna, you go by the oldest one. Of course you
could also remember by Yosef יוסף Yosef where he sat his brothers
at the meal, habechor kevichorato vehatzair ketzeirato הבכור כבכורתו והצעיר כצעירתו. habechor
kevichorato vehatzair ketzeirato. All right so now the Gemara גמרא Gemara says,
but now it has an interesting qualification on that. Amar Rav Ashi
אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, vehu d'maflig b'chachma vehu d'maflig b'zikna
והוא דמפליג בחכמה והוא דמפליג בזקנה. vehu d'maflig b'chachma vehu d'maflig b'zikna.
It's only if there's a significant gap, that the smarter one is
significantly smarter. If one guy,
the two brothers, they're too very smart, that guy he gets A+s,
his brother's gets As or something like that, that's not enough. You
do not use that as a basis of giving honor to a
younger brother over an older one if there's not a huge gap.
Now what's the reason? I mean if fundamentally it's an issue of
ordering according to their wisdom, it's fundamentally an intellectual discourse, why not?
But I think that the answer is pretty obvious and the Rashbam
רשב"ם Rashbam says this, I'll get to the Rashbam רשב"ם Rashbam in
a minute, but one answer, one point
is that wisdom,
how smart you are, is not as objectively measured as how old
you are. So if you're really going to give honor to somebody
because they're smart it's like actually how smart is he, you know,
and so on and unless there's some very obvious gap, this guy's
like, oh my god this guy's a genius, you know, whatever, you
know, is that really an appropriate reason to give honor to one
person over the thing that is much more measurable and clear and
defined, which is the question about the age, right? So unless it's
a significant gap, you're not going to do it. The other reason
is, of course, is because, you know, saying one person is older
and one person is younger, that's just like a reality that you
don't have control over. It's nothing to be embarrassed about. You might
as as a younger kid be annoyed that your older brother is
always the one who gets the respect, but you know, but it's
not like a person—it's not like some a personal critique of you,
right? To say, oh, we're going to give your younger brother respect
because he's smart, he's smarter than you are, right? So that's, you
know, that's like something that makes, you know, you feel, you know,
that's hurtful. So although you could also say, you know, I mean,
you know, brains comes from God as well, but it feels like
a more of a personal critique and judgment. So unless it's going
to be a significant gap, we're not going to do that, okay?
So that's on one hand. On the other hand, it's interesting that
it sort of says that the same—so why then when it says
that makes total sense why you need there to be a significant
gap in in brains, you know, before you honor a younger, smart
person, you know, smarter sort of sibling over a, you know, over
an older one who's not as smart. But how about the reverse?
Why does it say that when you're honoring the older one, like
at just a meal or something like that, why does it say
he have to be significantly older?
Because otherwise you'd want to honor the smarter one?
Ah. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says, right? Because normally you'd say like—based
certainly on what I just said, no, age is very quantifiable, whatever,
you gotta give some order, so you just go age order. Why
does it have to be a significant gap? So the רשב"ם Rashbam
says, that's a case where there is somebody who is much smarter.
And even so we said at a meal you give honor to
the older person. So now here's the scenario. He says, here you
are at a meal, you have one guy, your younger sibling is
like is like Albert Einstein, okay? He's a total
genius, okay?
You don't want to use us as examples here?
Oh sure, I'll use you as examples. Anyway, so he says, so
if the older brother is only a year older, you know what,
even if it's only a meal, you're going to give some honor
to him if he's so much smarter. He says, so there though
the being like older in age, if it's but if it's really
a significantly older brother, then again, since it's not a type of
an intellectual setting, you know, or context, you will continue to give,
you know, deference or honor to the older one.
You mean if there's a כהן Kohen there, right? Then he gets—he
leads the זימון? Zimun?
We're not talking about leading, we're talking about like seating order or
just other ways, you have to like say who do you serve
the—who
do you serve the—who do you serve the food to first? Other
ways of showing respect, okay? So the רשב"ם, Rashbam, I just want
to read you one line in the רשב"ם Rashbam about this, where
he basically makes this point. He says,
so he says like this. He says,
so he wants to know one minute,
right,
he wants to know what do you do והיכא דלא מופלג לא
האי בחכמה ולא האי בזקנה? ve-heikha de-la muflag lo hai be-chochmah ve-lo
hai be-ziknah?
There's nobody who's significantly older, significantly smarter. And it's a—נראה בעיני דבכל
מקום. nir'eh be-einai de-ve-chol makom.
The line starts with word בכל מקום. be-chol makom. I don't know
exactly where to say because it's like about 20 lines from the
bottom, okay? But he basically says by default, okay, you don't have
somebody significantly smarter, you don't have somebody whatever, דבכל מקום הולך אחר
זקנה. de-ve-chol makom holech achar ziknah.
Unless you've got a guy that's like a significant thing, you always
go by age. מידי דאמר רב אשי והוא דמופלג בחכמה והוא דמופלג
בזקנה. midei de-amar Rav Ashi ve-hu de-muflag be-chochmah ve-hu de-muflag be-ziknah. דהיכא
דהוי תרוייהו מופלגים, de-heikha de-havei tarveihu muflagim, when they're both have a
significant difference, then it depends, is it an intellectual discourse or is
it a meal? הולכין בישיבה אחר החכם ובמסיבה אחר הזקן. holchin bi-yeshivah
achar he-chacham u-vi-mesivah achar ha-zaken. ומכלל דהיכא דלא הוי תרוייהו מופלגים, u-michlal
de-heikha de-la havei tarveihu muflagim,
if there's no—there's no significant gap, לא האי ולא האי, lo hai
ve-lo hai, הולכין בכל מקום אחר אחד מהן. holchin be-chol makom achar
echad me-hen. Then
okay, you got to pick one, but which one? It's not clear
from the גמרא. Gemara. So he says ומדלא פירש איכא למימר דמסתמא
הולכין אחר הזקן, u-mi-de-lo peirash ika le-meimar de-mistama holchin achar ha-zaken, דבשביל
שבחור חכם קצת יותר ממנו, de-bishvil she-bachur chacham ktzat yoter mimenu, אין
לנו לבייש את הזקן. ein lanu le-vayesh et ha-zaken. Okay,
because that's one thing, like you know, say, oh, you know, he's
a little smarter than you. Like it's much clearer embarrassment to give
honor to somebody, you're saying I'm not so smart. All right? As—and
again, it's—age is not something you take personally and it's also more
quantifiable. והחכם אינו בוש בכך. ve-he-chacham eino bosh be-kach.
And if you give honor to the older one before the guy
who's a little bit smarter and younger, he's not—the חכם chacham isn't
embarrassed. מאחר שזקן ממנו יודע הוא שבשביל זקנותו חולקים לו כבוד. me-achar
she-zaken mimenu yodeia hu she-bishvil ziknuto cholkim lo kavod.
Like, you understand, that's a convention. You honor the older one, right?
But if you honor somebody who's smarter and younger,
that's—since the societal convention is to deference towards age, it seems much
more as a slap in the face. All right. So there would
need to be a huge gap before you did that. Yes, Michal?
Does the שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch or the גמרא Gemara discuss what
this חכמה chochmah is meant to be like? It sounds like a
humor or a strength like this חכמה chochmah to be like this
Einstein brilliance. Right. But isn't it learning, especially when they talk about
this kind of a ישיבה yeshiva as opposed to be פיקח pikeach
or to have דעה? de'ah? Aha. Really? But isn't it wisdom?
Well, okay, that's what I thought you were going to say. Wisdom
is different than intelligence. But in terms of learning, erudition, so those
are three different things. Intelligent, wisdom, and erudition. I don't think it's
erudition because we just got through the חכמניות chachmaniyot from בנות צלפחד.
Bnot Tzelafchad. And the point wasn't that they were book knowledgeable, they
knew a lot of knowledge of information. But I do agree, but
I do agree that it's probably more, more wisdom than intelligence. Right,
that's more, that's more correct. That is correct. Yeah.
Okay. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Where are we? Okay, תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל. Tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael.
We're talking now for רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael back to the גמרא.
Gemara. בנות צלפחד שקולות היו. Bnot Tzelafchad shkulot hayu. No, no, no.
The reason it gives different orders is not because one was a
context where it was all about intellectual discourse
and the other was a context of just, you know, סתם stam
ordering. So that's why it gave different orders. No, it's to actually
to emphasize that order doesn't matter because they were all equal. שקולות
היו. Shkulot hayu. The גמרא Gemara does this elsewhere by משה ואהרן.
Moshe v'Aharon. Sometimes it says משה ואהרן, Moshe v'Aharon, sometimes says אהרן
ומשה Aharon u'Moshe to tell you that they were of equal weight.
Which doesn't mean that they were of equal, like they were all
carbon copies, right? They could have had different talents. משה'ס Moshe's talents
were different than אהרן'ס Aharon's talents. But it means that none of
them and their dealing with this issue, you know, who do you
give, who do you say is more important than the other? But
no one's more important than anyone. Each one had different reasons why
they were of equal value.
שקולות היו. Shkulot hayu. שנאמר ותהיינה. Shene'emar vat'hiyenah. ותהיינה בנות צלפחד Vat'hiyenah
bnot Tzelafchad and then lists their names. מחלה נעה Machlah Noa etc.
הויה אחת לכולן. Havayah achat l'chulan. They were all of one sort
of being. They all had one of equal weight.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. בנות צלפחד
הותרו להינשא לכל השבטים. Bnot Tzelafchad huteru linasei l'chol hashvatim. Okay, so
now from for many, for a long time I've been telling you
that the פסוק pasuk that says that, you know, you have to
marry somebody within your own tribe, right, so that the property doesn't
go out of the tribe, that was only said to that generation.
Other generations were free to marry outside, which is not in the
פסוקים, p'sukim, it's a דרשה drasha of חז"ל, Chazal, right, which of
course just, you know, goes to that whole issue about disturbing the
נחלה. nachalah. והעברתם את נחלתו לבתו. V'havartem et nachalatot l'vito. But here
the גמרא Gemara actually seems to be saying the opposite. Okay, in
the end it'll get back to what I was telling you, but
it starts off by seeming to say the opposite. That בנות צלפחד
Bnot Tzelafchad did not have to marry within their tribe. Seeming to
go directly against פשט pshat of the פסוקים. p'sukim. They could marry
whoever they wanted. So you had a question Michal? Okay, so it
says: בנות צלפחד הותרו להינשא לכל השבטים. Bnot Tzelafchad huteru linasei l'chol
hashvatim. They could have married from any tribe. שנאמר לטוב בעיניהן תהיינה
לנשים, Shene'emar latov b'eineihen tihyenah l'nashim, right? Marry whomever you want, sort
of ignoring the end of the פסוק pasuk that says אך למשפחת
מטה אביהם. ach l'mishpachat mateh avihem. Oh, just keep it in the
tribe. No, no, no, bracket that. Marry whoever you want, okay? So
the גמרא Gemara says, so, so the
גמרא Gemara says אלא מני מקיים אך למשפחת מטה אביהם תהיינה לנשים?
ella mani mikayem ach l'mishpachat mateh avihem tihyenah l'nashim? It's like a
kid, he listens to the first part, he doesn't listen to the
but part, right? Okay, so אלא מני... ella mani... oh, we just
did that. תהיינה
לנשים. tihyenah l'nashim. עצה טובה השיאנו הכתוב שלא ינשאו אלא ההגון להם.
Eitza tovah hesianu hakatuv shelo yinasei ella ha-hagun lahem. It says, you
know, but my advice would be, you can marry whoever you want.
My advice is, marry within the tribes. But it's
interesting because it's by framing ההגון להם, ha-hagun lahem, it's more sort
of saying like, you know, sit because like you're more likely to
find somebody of a similar background, somebody who's a better match if
you stay within your tribe than if you marry somebody else, you
know. But it doesn't sound like from the פסוקים, p'sukim, right, it's
the reason you marry within the tribes is so the נחלה nachalah
doesn't pass out. Maybe it means הגון hagun from that perspective. Not
just out of interest of the tribe should you marry within the
tribe. Out of the interest of your family and your father's family
also, it would be in your best interest to stay within the
tribe, but we're not demanding that. But I think it is interesting
the way it's phrased as הגון להם. hagun lahem. Is that הגון
hagun because of the issue of the property passing out? Or is
that הגון hagun because of some assumption like you're more likely to
find somebody, you know, who works for you if you have a
sort of similar type of a family connection and of a background?
Yes?
A couple of things, you know, one is just yesterday we were
saying they're צדקניות, tzidkaniyot, so לנשים אלא הגון להם l'nashim ella hagun
lahem and it's like God tells them, just do that, so then
they just do what they're supposed to do or what they're going
to be צדקניות tzidkaniyot which is interesting from that perspective looking at
what God told them.
I know, but you are right, it echoes the הגון להם hagun
lahem before, and now it's sort of saying that decision of waiting
for the right person was something that they were sort of being
advised by God about, right? So they just followed God's advice. That
is correct. That is correct.
Which then you could say, well, look, God tells us what to
do.
Exactly.
Exactly. What's a צדיק tzaddik other than somebody who just does, not
only somebody who just does.
Yes, and within
the משפחה, mishpacha, and it's not just the tribe, right?
It's also the same משפחה, mishpacha, yeah.
It's a bit more local than that.
That's true too, that's true too. Yeah, I mean and the גמרא
Gemara also does sort of want, you know again, I mean it's
against our sort of knowledge of genetics and the types of problems
that comes when you marry too close relatives, but the גמרא Gemara
in general likes, thinks you know, wants people to be marrying like
uncles to be marrying nieces and people to be marrying like close
within the family, right? So maybe that's also part of the הגון
hagun for them. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
מתיב רבה, metiv Rava, so רבה Rava challenged this. So now we
have a ברייתא, baraita, and here's what the ברייתא baraita says: אמור
אליהם, emor aleihem, say to them, like,
so this is about a פסוק pasuk by, what do you call
it,
by שחוטי חוץ, shuchutei chutz, the פסוק pasuk is אמור אליהם, emor
aleihem, איש איש מבית ישראל... ish ish mibeit Yisrael... wait, what one
time what is it?
I mean there's אמור אליהם...
emor aleihem...
wait, where's the פסוק pasuk the רשב"ם Rashbam quotes it? אמור
אליהם לדורותיכם כל איש אשר יקרב מכל זרעכם אל הקדשים אשר יקדישו
בני ישראל וטומאתו עליו, emor aleihem ledoroteichem kol ish asher yikrav mikol
zar'achem el hakodashim asher yakdishu benei Yisrael utumato alav, oh it's about
being טמא tamei when you're engaging קדשים. kodashim. So here's the דרשה:
drasha: אמור
אליהם emor aleihem say to them, ראותן העומדים על הר סיני, re'otan
ha'omdim al Har Sinai, so אמור אליהם emor aleihem means the people
that you're dealing with right now, those are at the foot of
הר סיני. Har Sinai. Okay, and then the פסוק pasuk continues לדורותיכם,
ledoroteichem, this is not by בנות צלפחד, Bnot Tzelofchad, this is by
טומאה tumah and קדשים, kodashim, for your future generations, אלו דורות הבאים.
elu dorot haba'im. So tell them for future generations, meaning what you
משה Moshe are going to tell them now about the מצווה mitzvah
of קדשים kodashim and טומאה tumah applies to them and to future
generations. Now we're going to use that though as a paradigm and
to say that unless you have explicit information otherwise, any מצווה mitzvah
in the תורה Torah apply to that generation and to future generations.
אם נאמר אבות למה נאמר בנים ואם נאמר בנים למה נאמר אבות?
im ne'emar avot lama ne'emar banim ve'im ne'emar banim lama ne'emar avot?
Why does it have to be clear that it applies both to
the fathers and the kids? Say one and I'll infer the other.
No, מפני שיש באבות מה שאין בבנים ויש בבנים מה שאין באבות.
mipnei sheyesh ba'avot ma she'ein babanim veyesh babanim ma she'ein ba'avot.
Sometimes you'll have a case of מצווה mitzvah that applies to the
fathers and not to the children, applies to the generation of דור
סיני Dor Sinai and not future generations, and sometimes you'll have מצווה
mitzvah that applies to future generations and not to the generation of
הר
סיני. Har Sinai. So therefore since sometimes you have something that's only
one and not the other, it has to tell you that as
a rule it always applies to both unless you have explicit indication
otherwise.
I mean this applies to
קדשים, kodashim, right? Because they were only allowed to eat meat then,
that generation, if they brought the קרבן korban to the משכן. Mishkan.
Right, that could be. Okay, so anyway, so because sometimes you get
only one and not the other. So now, ויש בבנים מה שאין
באבות, באבות הוא אומר. veyesh babanim ma she'ein ba'avot, ba'avot hu omer.
Now where is a case of a מצווה mitzvah that applied only
to the generation of the מדבר Midbar and not future generations that
you need to say that, you know, again the rule is always
both? Because it says וכל בת יורשת נחלה, vechol bat yoreshet nachala,
because any daughter who inherits, like, you know, whatever, ממשפחת מטה אביה
תהיה לאשה, mimishpachat mateh aviha tihyeh le'isha,
and the גמרא Gemara says, and this is what I've been telling
you since the beginning of the פרק, perek, that was only for
the generation חז"ל Chazal say of מדבר סיני. Midbar Sinai. It certainly
doesn't sound like that at all and of course it certainly means
that you're going to have problems of sections of a tribe belonging
to other tribes, but חז"ל Chazal nevertheless understood, you know, that no,
we are not going to restrict the women, they weren't meant to
be restricted in that way and that that מצווה mitzvah only applied
to that generation of בנות צלפחד. Bnot Tzelofchad. Did they know that
at the time?
What? I mean, they knew that at the time or is that
a later דרשה drasha of חז"ל Chazal retrojecting it back in?
It's a later דרשה drasha of חז"ל Chazal
like a thousand years later.
Fine, but that's by a lot of things. Okay, whatever, but we're
understanding that that's the way the פסוק pasuk was meant. Okay, it
was meant only for the generation of דור המדבר. Dor HaMidbar. והרבה
מצוות נצטוו בנים שלא נצטוו אבות, veharbe mitzvot nitztavu banim shelo nitztavu
avot,
and we don't even have to mention, there're clearly מצוות mitzvot that
apply to the later generations and not to the generation of the
מדבר. Midbar. The רשב"ם Rashbam says first of all any מצווה mitzvah
that deals with ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that deals with ביכורים bikurim
and תרומות ומעשרות terumot uma'asrot and all those things, right, that only
applies to future generations. So since there are some that apply only
to the generation of the מדבר Midbar and some only to the
future generations, we need to tell you in this פסוק, pasuk, tells
you the paradigm, the rule is it always applies to both unless
you know explicitly otherwise.
Yes, but it's not exactly a good example there, though, because it
doesn't apply to the fathers like if they happen to be...
Right, it's by chance, right, exactly... future generations. Right, I realize that
too. It's the circumstances aren't relevant but in theory it would apply,
right. So, yeah, I don't know what to say to that but
you're absolutely correct. But anyway, so the גמרא Gemara continues and it
says, okay, הוצרך לומר אבות הוצרך לומר בנים. hutzrach lomar avot hutzrach
lomar banim. It has to tell you both, that in general the
rule is both. קתני מיהת, katani mihat, the ברייתא baraita nevertheless teaches
us, באבות הוא אומר וכל בת יורשת נחלה. ba'avot hu omer vechol
bat yoreshet nachala.
So you see that it's saying very clear that that applied to
that generation, not to future generations, but that it's a restriction, it's
not just advice, it's a... Okay, so צריכי למו וצריכי לבנים. itzrichi
lamo veitzrichi labanim. It has to tell you both. That in general
the rule is both. דתני מיהא datni miha the ברייתא braita nevertheless
teaches us ואבות הוא אומר ve'avot hu omer וכל בת יורשת נחלה,
vechol bat yoireshet nachala, so you see that it's saying very clear
that that applied to that generation, not the future generations, but that
it's a restriction. It's not just advice, it's a real restriction. So
the גמרא gemara says meaning what that the only wait the what
that you can only marry within the tribe. You said בנות צלפחד
benot tzelofchad could have married anyone. He says it's very clear. We
were restricted. So the גמרא Gemara says meaning what that you can
only marry within the tribe. You said בנות צלפחד Benot Tzelofchad could
have married anyone. He says it's very clear. No, that they, that's
a מצוה, mitzvah, that they were obligated to marry within the tribe.
It wasn't just advice. You had to marry within the tribe, at
least for that generation.
So it says הוא מותיב לה והוא מפרק לה, hu moitiv lah
vehu mefarek lah, he asked it but and he gave the answer.
לבר מבנות צלפחד. levar miBenot Tzelofchad. No, no, no, anybody else. בנות
צלפחד Benot Tzelofchad because maybe because of a reward, because that they
were so צדקניות וחכמניות tzidkaniyot vechachmaniyot or whatever. So it's very interesting,
right? Any future generation you can marry anybody you want. בנות צלפחד
Benot Tzelofchad marry anybody you want. Advice, marry within the tribe, marry
your father's family, but really marry anybody. The only people to who
that מצוה mitzvah said that you have to marry within the tribe
is any other of the women who piggybacked on the initiative of
בנות צלפחד Benot Tzelofchad and were in a similar situation at that
generation and also received a נחלה, nachala, those women in that generation
had to marry within the tribe. But future generations marry who you
want, בנות צלפחד Benot Tzelofchad marry who you want, but the advice
is marry within the tribe. Okay. Very interesting read of really shrinking
the scope of those פסוקים. pesukim. All right. So it says like
this. אמר מר, באבות הוא אומר. amar mar, be'avot hu omer. Now
we're going to go and look at this דרשה. drasha. This other
דרשה drasha that we've brought in in passing. באבות הוא אומר וכל
בת יורשת נחלה. be'avot hu omer vechol bat yoireshet nachala. באבות אין,
בבנים לא. be'avot in, bevanim lo. מאי משמע? mai mashma? So now
we're finally asking, where do you get this idea that marrying within
the tribe for a woman who inherits property was only limited to
that generation of the מדבר? midbar? So אמר ליה רבא זוטא לרב
אשי. amar lei Rabba Zuta leRav Ashi. I'm sorry, skipped a line.
מאי משמע? mai mashma? אמר רבא אמר קרא: זה הדבר אשר צוה
ה'. amar Rava amar kra: zeh hadavar asher tziva Hashem. This is
the matter. When and that's then says marry only within the tribe.
That's at the end of במדבר. Bamidbar. דבר זה, davar zeh, so
זה zeh is limiting. דבר זה לא יהא נוהג אלא בדור זה.
davar zeh lo yehei noheg ela bedor zeh. Okay, that's a clearly,
you know, חז"ל Chazal had a read and reason to want to
read it that way. This, it's limited to these immediate circumstances. So
now we're going to say: really? Every time it says זה הדבר,
zeh hadavar, it means only in this only right now? So אמר
ליה רבא זוטא לרב אשי: amar lei Rabba Zuta leRav Ashi: אלא
מעתה, זה הדבר דשחוטי חוץ, ella mei'ata, zeh hadavar deshchutei chutz, right?
It says זה הדבר אשר צוה ה'
איש איש מבית ישראל אשר ישחט שור או כשב או עז במחנה
zeh hadavar asher
tziva Hashem ish ish mibeit Yisrael asher yishchat shor o khesev o
ez bamachaneh or אשר ישחט מחוץ למחנה. asher yishchat michutz lamachaneh. So
if somebody basically brings a sacrifice and it's קדשים kodshim and it
hasn't brought it as a קרבן, korban, then they get כרת. karet.
So that starts with זה הדבר. zeh hadavar. So you mean to
tell me that only applies to that generation of דור המדבר? dor
hamidbar? אלא מעתה, זה הדבר דשחוטי חוץ הכי נמי לא יהא נוהג
אלא בדור זה? ella mei'ata, zeh hadavar deshchutei chutz hachi nami lo
yehei noheg ela bedor zeh? שאני התם, shani hatam, no there's different
דכתיב dechtiv לדורותיכם. ledoroteichem. Okay there it says explicitly. Right, זה הדבר
אשר צוה ה', zeh hadavar asher tziva Hashem, what's the פסוק? pasuk?
לדורותיכם. ledoroteichem. Michael, what's the פסוק? pasuk? אמור אליהם לדורותיכם. emor aleihem
ledoroteichem. Is that it? ויקרא Vayikra what?
י"ז... yud-zayin... דורותם. dorotam. Where is it?
י"ז yud-zayin what?
Oh, לדורותם. ledorotam.
Did I say לדורותיכם? ledoroteichem? ויקרא Vayikra what?
כ"ב? khaf-bet? No, not כ"ב. khaf-bet. י"ז ו'. yud-zayin vav.
זה הדבר אשר צוה ה' לאמר איש
איש מבית ישראל
אשר ישחט שור או כשב או עז במחנה או אשר ישחט מחוץ
למחנה ואל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו
zeh hadavar asher tziva Hashem leimor ish ish mibeit Yisrael asher yishchat
shor o khesev o ez bamachaneh o asher yishchat michutz lamachaneh ve'el
petach
ohel moed lo hevi'o
blah blah blah להקריב קרבן lehakriv korban למען אשר יביאו בני ישראל
את זבחיהם אשר הם זבחים על פני השדה ולא יזבחו עוד את
זבחיהם לשעירם אשר הם זנים אחריהם חקת עולם תהיה זאת להם לדורותם.
lema'an asher yavi'u benei Yisrael et zivcheihem asher hem zovchim al pnei
hasadeh velo yizbechu od et zivcheihem lase'irim asher hem zonim achareihem chukat
olam tihiyeh zot lahem ledorotam. Okay,
so it says לדורותם. ledorotam. So we know it's not meant to
be limited one minute to that generation. So זה הדבר דראשי המטות
הכי נמי, zeh hadavar deroshei hamatot hachi nami, how about זה הדבר
zeh hadavar by where it speaks about the, you know, about the
נדרים, nedarim, right? אל ראשי המטות לבני ישראל el roshei hamatot livnei
Yisrael like by מטות מסעי, matot masei, מטות, matot, right? זה הדבר
אשר צוה ה' איש כי ידר נדר או השבע שבעה לאסר אסר
על נפשו, zeh hadavar asher tziva Hashem ish ki yidor neder o
hishava shevua le'esor issar al nafsho, right? So you mean to tell
me that whole פרשה parsha of נדרים nedarim or of התרת נדרים
hatarat nedarim which is also what we learn from there, that whole
פרשה parsha was only for דור המדבר? dor hamidbar? הכי נמי דלא
יהא נוהג אלא בדור זה? hachi nami delo yehei noheg ela bedor
zeh? בדור זה? bedor zeh? אמר ליה: amar lei: No, ההוא יליף
זה זה מהתם. hahu yalif zeh zeh mehatam. No, since we got
the זה הדבר zeh hadavar by שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz and it
says לדורותם, ledorotam, then the זה הדבר zeh hadavar by the נדרים
nedarim is linked by גזירה שוה gezeira shava and it also means
for a future generation. Which of course... all right, then say the
same about בנות צלפחד. Benot Tzelofchad. One minute. So the
גמרא Gemara says אלא האי נמי נילף זה זה מהתם. ella hai
nami neilaf zeh zeh mehatam. Let's say the same by בנות צלפחד.
Benot Tzelofchad. No. האי מאי? hai mai? What are you talking about?
בשלמא התם אצטריך גזירה שוה. bishlama hatam itrich gezeira shava. So there
you needed
the
גזירה שוה gezeira shava to tell you the idea future generations since
it shouldn't have said the word
זה zeh at all. It would have saved me the... and therefore
once we're going to learn out other things, we're going to learn
out future generations and the purpose of the זה zeh was not
to be a limiting word. The purpose of the זה zeh was
to create the גזרה שוה gezeirah shavah to allow me to learn
out these other things. הכא, Hacha, so that's why you have the
זה zeh there. הכא, Hacha, למאי איצטריך? lemai itztrich? Here, if it
wanted to say it applies to all generations, don't say זה zeh
and make a גזרה שוה, gezeirah shavah, just don't say anything, and
I would have said it applies to all generations. לישתוק קרא מיניה
Lishtok kra minei and let it just be quiet, ואנא ידענא דלדורות
הוא, ve’ana yadana deldoros hu, and I would have known it's future
generations. So since it says זה zeh and there's no need to
learn anything out from these other פרשיות parshiyos of שחוטי חוץ shechutei
chutz and נדרים, nedarim, right, then the only purpose of saying זה
zeh is to limit it to that generation. Whereas in the other
two cases, it said the זה zeh to make a גזרה שוה
gezeirah shavah because we're going to learn something, and I know it's
not limited to that generation because it adds the word לדורותם ledorosam
by one of them. Okay, there was a question. Charlie?
Yes, so the offerings outside of the
משכן, Mishkan, outside, yeah. Immediately after we entered the land, that was
way for 14 years. Right. So it did apply all generations?
It goes back to Jenna's point, which is it does apply even
though the circumstances aren't always there. Okay, anyway let's see as the
גמרא Gemara continues. Okay. So, okay. ומאי גזרה שוה? U’mai gezeirah shavah?
Now what's the גזרה שוה gezeirah shavah of the זה זה zeh
zeh of שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz and נדרים nedarim that is needed
and that's why the זה zeh is written to make the גזרה
שוה gezeirah shavah and the זה zeh is not meant to limit
it to that time because I have that word לדורותם? ledorosam? So
what is the גזרה שוה gezeirah shavah coming to do? דתניא, Detanya,
we learn in a ברייתא: braisa: נאמר כאן זה הדבר Ne’emar kan
zeh hadavar ונאמר להלן זה הדבר. v’ne’emar lehallan zeh hadavar. It says
זה הדבר zeh hadavar by the נדרים nedarim and it says זה
הדבר zeh hadavar by the שחוטי חוץ. shechutei chutz. מה להלן אהרן
ובניו וכל ישראל, Mah lehallan Aharon uvanav vechol Yisrael, it says by
the שחוטי חוץ, shechutei chutz, how does the פרשה parshah begin again?
זה הדבר אשר צוה ה'. Zeh hadavar asher tzivah Hashem. No, the
beginning of it says... oh now I closed it, but... probably וידבר
ה' אל משה לאמר דבר אל אהרן ואל בניו ואל כל בני
ישראל... Vayidaber Hashem el Moshe leimor dabeir el Aharon v'el banav v'el
kol bnei Yisrael... what is it? Let's take a look. Which one?
The שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz one, ויקרא
י"ז. Vayikra yud zayin. ויקרא
י"ז.
Vayikra yud
zayin.
דבר אל אהרן ואל בניו ואל כל בני ישראל ואמרת אליהם זה
הדבר אשר צוה ה'. Dabeir el Aharon v’el banav v’el kol bnei
Yisrael v’amarta aleihem zeh hadavar asher tzivah Hashem. So, אל אהרן ואל
בניו ואל כל בני ישראל. el Aharon v’el banav v’el kol bnei
Yisrael. So that's what it says there. So מה
להלן אהרן ובניו וכל ישראל אף כאן, mah lehallan Aharon uvanav vechol
Yisrael af kan, same true by the case of נדרים. nedarim. Now
what does that mean? What do I halachically learn from that? We'll
see in a minute.
ומה להלן
אהרן ובניו וכל ישראל אף כאן אהרן ובניו וכל ישראל. U’mah lehallan
Aharon uvanav vechol Yisrael af kan Aharon uvanav vechol Yisrael. ומה כאן
ראשי המטות, U’mah kan rashei hamatos, the same way by the נדרים
nedarim it was ראשי המטות, rashei hamatos, אף להלן ראשי המטות af
lehallan rashei hamatos by the case of שחוטי חוץ. shechutei chutz. Okay.
So what do I learn about from that? What does that tell
me other than historically who it was given to? So now we're
going to say what halachically that means. אמר מר: Amar mar: מה
להלן אהרן ובניו וכל ישראל אף כאן אהרן ובניו וכל ישראל. Mah
lehallan Aharon uvanav vechol Yisrael af kan Aharon uvanav vechol Yisrael. למאי
הלכתא? Lemai hilchasa? What's the point? For what halachic implication is this?
אמר רב אחא בר יעקב: Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov: לומר שהפרת
נדרים בשלושה הדיוטות. lomar she’haforas nedarim bishloshah hedyotos. Okay, so here's the
point. We learn from... because the general question: why is the case
of נדרים nedarim said to ראשי המטות, rashei hamatos, the heads of
the tribes? What's the significance? So the classic דרשה drashah of חז"ל
Chazal number one is: לא יחל דברו, lo yachel devaro, which if
you make a נדר neder your words cannot become like voided or,
you know, desecrated, or you cannot. So the דרשה drashah is: הוא
אינו מיחל, hu eino meichal, you cannot go ahead and violate and
void your words, אבל אחרים מתירין ומיחלין לו, aval acheirim matirin umeichalin
lo, or, you know, others can go ahead and do התרת נדרים,
hataras nedarim, can basically effectively void your words. So we learn a
דרשה drashah from that פרשה parshah as we learn the concept of
התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim. You go to a חכם, chacham, you say
had I thought about this, had I anticipated this, I never would
have made it, I regret it, and other people therefore מתירין לו.
matirin lo. So, and from there we say ראשי המטות. rashei hamatos.
Who are these others that are מתירין לו? matirin lo? So basically
it's like a חכם, chacham, somebody who is like a sage or
whatever, that's what we sort of identify that's the meaning of ראשי
המטות. rashei hamatos. So now that's the whole background. Now we know
what ראשי המטות rashei hamatos means and specifically in the context of
התרת נדרים hataras nedarim which we're reading into those פסוקים. pesukim. Now
that we bring in אהרן ובניו וכל ישראל, Aharon uvanav vechol Yisrael,
we say it's not limited to ראשי המטות. rashei hamatos. התרת נדרים
Hataras nedarim can be done by people who is not a חכם,
chacham, but then you would need not just an individual, you would
need more. So you would need a בית דין, beis din, so
you would need three. Okay. I actually thought that maybe the בית
דין beis din idea was אהרן Aharon was one, two sons is
three, but אהרן ובניו Aharon uvanav are not הדיוטות. hedyotos. But that's
בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. But תוספות Tosafos says no, once we know
that it's more than one, so you're not going to say two,
halachically the next sort of significant group, exactly, is three. So that's
what we learn by bringing in בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael that you
can have a בית דין beis din of הדיוטות hedyotos to do
התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim. Okay. Okay, so למאי הלכתא? Le'mai hilkhata?
אמר רב יעקב: Amar Rav Yaakov: לומר שהפרת נדרים בשלושה הדיוטות. lomar
she'hafarat nedarim b'shlosha hedyotot. וראשי המטות כתיב ביה. Ve'rashei hamatot ktiv bei.
So what do you do with ראשי המטות? rashei hamatot? That suggests
not הדיוטות. hedyotot. So the גמרא Gemara says כדאמר רב חסדא אמר
רב יוחנן k'de'amar Rav Chisda amar Rabbi Yochanan ביחיד מומחה. b'yachid mumche.
He's going to say later on in a similar discussion that if
you have one person who's an expert, who's like a
חכם, chakham, okay, that then exactly what qualifies as a מומחה mumche
is a separate discussion. Anyway, then he can do it alone. So
הכא נמי ביחיד מומחה. hacha nami b'yachid mumche. He says that elsewhere
but it's the same as true
here, the ראשי המטות rashei hamatot is to say if you have
a מומחה, mumche, somebody who's a real תלמיד חכם, talmid chakham, an
expert, maybe it also means they've been given certain authority like the
ראשי המטות rashei hamatot have been given certain authority, then you can
do התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim with one person. But if you don't,
then you have בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, which we're reading in from
the other פרשה parasha to say you can have three can do
it as well. Okay, now how about the other דרשה drasha for
שחוטי חוץ? shchutei chutz? ומה ראשי המטות כאן אף להלן ראשי המטות.
u'ma rashei hamatot kan af le'halan rashei hamatot. So what do you
do by bringing the idea of ראשי המטות rashei hamatot into שחוטי
חוץ? shchutei chutz? What does that have to do with שחיטהing shechita
things outside the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? למאי הלכתא? Le'mai hilkhata? For
what הלכה? halakha? אמר רב ששת: Amar Rav Sheshet: לומר lomar to
tell you שיש שאלה בהקדש. she'yesh she'eila b'hekdesh. Ah, to tell you
the same way you could do התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim by a
נדר neder to make something forbidden like a נדר neder I'm all
fruit is forbidden to me, so you can do התרת נדרים hatarat
nedarim by if you're מקדיש makdish something. I am מקדיש makdish this
animal to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Now for people who remember
going back to when we learned נדרים, Nedarim, the whole category of
a נדר neder is borrowed from the idea of הקדש. hekdesh. A
classic way of making a נדר neder is to say קונם, konam,
you know these fruit are קונם, konam, and קונם konam is like
a short version of קרבן. korban. The same way your words can
make something into a קרבן korban and sanctify it, you can give
it a similar type of a status, not that it belongs to
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, not that it's going to be brought
as a קרבן, korban, but that it has sort of the forbidden
nature of a קרבן korban and it's off limits and that's through
your words and that's a נדר. neder. Okay, but it's all a
similar world of how your words can change the status of an
object. And that actually is called הפלאה. hafla'ah. איש כי יפלא לנדור
נדר נזיר. Ish ki yafli lindor neder nazir. הפלאה Hafla'ah is a
verbal act that changes the status of something. Okay, being a נזיר
nazir by the way is also an act of הפלאה. hafla'ah. You
make yourself into a
נזיר nazir by your verbal act. So the question is: Oh, so
if I can do התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim on my thing making
this fruit forbidden on me, maybe I can do התרת נדרים hatarat
nedarim on all acts of הפלאה, hafla'ah, on all verbal acts that
change status? So actually the גמרא Gemara discusses this a good deal
by like תרומה. terumah. I מפריש תרומה mafrish terumah and then I
have regret and for whatever reason maybe I can retroactively get it
undone. Okay, but how about other things like if I give something
to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, that's maybe not so clear? 'Cause
if I'm doing it to תרומה terumah that's still at this stage
like between me and God and it changed the halakhic status, but
like for example if I give that תרומה terumah to a כהן,
kohen, once I give it to a כהן kohen I've made it
a real thing, right, it's like it's now he owns it, right,
it's out of my control, like I can't really now go ahead
and retroactively change its status. So if I מקדיש makdish something to
a בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, right, can I go ahead and now
it belongs to the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? I mean maybe it
depends on the type of הקדש, hekdesh, but you know can I
now go ahead and undo it through
התרת נדרים? hatarat nedarim? Also הקדש hekdesh is extremely weighty, so you
might think that you know when you're playing with הקדש hekdesh you
don't get a chance to have wait, wait, I want to reconsider
that. Like you know maybe that's the weightiness of it makes it
final. So this is a question: Is there התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim
by הקדש? hekdesh? So the גמרא Gemara is actually going to say
it's a debate of בית שמאי ובית הלל. Beit Shammai u'Beit Hillel.
So the reason to make the דרשה drasha of ראשי המטות rashei
hamatot and apply it to the case of the קרבנות korbanot is
not so much for the הלכה halakha of שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz
but more because the הלכה halakha of שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz is
talking about sanctified קרבנות korbanot and to tell you oh, you know
what, you can do התרת נדרים. hatarat nedarim. We make a גזירה
שוה gezeira shava and you can undo that. And actually just one
more second, and actually this is a way you could get out
of ever being over on the איסור issur of שחוטי חוץ. shchutei
chutz. You מקדיש makdish a קרבן, korban, you שחט shacht it outside
of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you know you're now being told
that you're חייב כרת. chayav kareth. And I didn't mean to, so
you go to a חכם, chakham, you know had I realized that
I was going to be חייב כרת chayav kareth I never would
have sanctified that
animal. Now really what you never would have done is you never
would have שחטed shacht the animal outside the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
but anyway it becomes an interesting way that retroactively you could get
out of, you know let's say I make something תרומה terumah and
I eat it as a non-כהן, kohen, can I now go and
undo it? Like it really raises interesting questions. But anyway, but we
learn fundamentally from the link that you can do התרת נדרים hatarat
nedarim on הקדש. hekdesh. הרב דוד Rav David had a question.
Would it be accurate halachically to describe the act of קידושין kiddushin
as an act of הפלאה? hafla'ah?
Well, so, yeah, it would be partially accurate. Meaning, the beginning of
מסכת קידושין Masechet Kiddushin and the whole language of קידושין, kiddushin, and
רש״י Rashi emphasizes this as well,
there's a speech act associated with קידושין, kiddushin, it's the הרי את
מקודשת לי. Harei at mekudeshes li. And that speech act seems to
be more than the normal revealing what your intent is that exists
by other types of transactions. And there definitely is a reason to
think that חז״ל Chazal understood that קידושין kiddushin is not just the
giving of an object of value, the giving of a ring, but
it's also a speech act combined with it, borrowed from this world
of הקדש hekdesh and הפלאה, hafla'ah, so yes, there definitely seems to
be that approach within קידושין. kiddushin. Yes. Love it.
Right. So, some people take this idea and relate that then in
their conception of objects in general, it's really a speech act that
effects a קנין kinyan together with an action and הפלאה. hafla'ah. In
other words, הפלאה hafla'ah is a subset of a kind of...
No. Some types of speech acts have... do transfer, like when you're
מקדיש makdish something to בדק הבית. Bedek HaBayis. And by the way,
we're going to get to a different thing, which is a... which
is the whole story about the best dead bequest, about דברי שכיב
מרע, divrei shchiv meira, which are words that are all about קנין,
kinyan, they're not about status. Right? הפלאה hafla'ah is not just a
speech act. It's a speech act that changes the status of an
object, where the דברי שכיב מרע divrei shchiv meira that are כתובים
ומסורים דמי, kesuvim u'mesurim dami, that have the effect like you did
a קנין, kinyan, is not really... I don't know, maybe somebody compares
it to הפלאה, hafla'ah, but it's seen as completely different. It's fundamentally
is not about the status of the object, it's fundamentally is about
transferring the ownership. But yeah, sometimes those things do intersect.
And so the person who had the...
Right. Yeah, but it's not a different type of an object that's
just owned by somebody else. Yeah.
So I wanted to say, so it's interesting because if I try
to actually do a תמורה t'murah on תרומה... trumah... A תמורה... t'murah...
Yeah. And the חומש. chomesh. So what I really should do is
just undo it to begin with, which is שאלה, she'ilah, right?
You could do that, but it's
interesting that you mentioned that because תמורה t'murah is the... one of
the reasons that בית שמאי Beis Shammai says that there is no...
well, we'll... I'll skip that. I'll get back to תמורה t'murah in
a minute. I want to read in the גמרא. Gemara. Yeah.
And if you can annul the הקדש, hekdesh, then the value of
the הקדש, hekdesh, then you would not pay the חומש chomesh that
you would have to... if you redeemed it.
That's similar to Michael's point. Yeah, I mean, yeah, so you can...
The question is is that even if it's possible, how, you know,
there's a lot of reasons other than... like how... how loosely would...
how widely would this be used? Right? Because obviously... So anyway, but
that's why it's debated. So let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara.
So אמר רב ששת למה שיש שאלה בהקדש. Amar Rav Sheshes l'ma
she'yesh she'yla b'hekdesh. That you can actually... שאלה she'yla means like you
go to a חכם chacham and you sort of you, you know,
you express your regret and you essentially ask for it to be
undone. Okay? And that
applies to הקדש. hekdesh. So בית שמאי דאמרי אין שאלה בהקדש. Beis
Shammai d'amri ein she'yla b'hekdesh. How about בית שמאי Beis Shammai says
that that doesn't work? Where do you know that בית שמאי Beis
Shammai says it doesn't work? דתנן: Detnan: בית שמאי אומרים הקדש טעות
הקדש. Beis Shammai omrim hekdesh taus hekdesh. If you make something הקדש
hekdesh by accident, it's still הקדש. hekdesh. ובית הלל אומרים אינו הקדש.
U'veish Hillel omrim eino hekdesh. It's not. An example would be somebody
says,
I'm מקדיש makdish the ox... I... like the... that's walk... the first
ox that's going to walk out of my house. Makes us think
of יפתח. Yiftach. Yeah, I know. Anyway, um, is הקדש. hekdesh. Really
is the יפתח Yiftach case. I mean, that's exactly... that would be
a perfect example, right? And you think it's going to be your
black ox and it winds up being your daughter. No, but in
the גמרא, Gemara, in the cases, and it winds up being your
white ox. So you anyway, sanctifying it because you were assuming it
was something and it was actually something other. Okay? And it wasn't
what you had in mind when you said it. So בית הלל
Beis Hillel says, well, it wasn't what you were thinking, like all
types of cases of הפלאה. hafla'ah. We know the principle is נדר
פיו ולבו שווים. neder piv v'libo shavim. What you say has to
be in sync with what you're thinking. And when it isn't, the
הקדש hekdesh doesn't take effect. And בית שמאי Beis Shammai says, I
don't care. הקדש hekdesh is so weighty that when you say those
words, even if it's not in sync with what you're thinking, it
still takes effect. One of the places בית שמאי Beis Shammai learns
this from is by תמורה. t'murah. Right? By תמורה, t'murah, I am
trying to transfer the קדושה kedushah from animal A to animal B.
And what happens is animal B becomes הקדש hekdesh and animal A
remains הקדש. hekdesh. Now the only reason I was doing it was
I thought I was going to be able to remove it from
animal A and put it on animal B. Had I known that
it would have stayed on animal A, I never would have done
this exchange. And nevertheless, even though it was not what I was
thinking, animal B still becomes הקדש. hekdesh. So בית שמאי Beis Shammai
says, you see from that the principle that הקדש בטעות הקדש. hekdesh
b'taus hekdesh. Now if an obvious הקדש... hekdesh... I don't know, it's
a גזירת הכתוב g'zeiras hakatuv by תמורה. t'murah. If an obvious הקדש
hekdesh that is in error, it's obvious at the time that it's
in error, is still קדוש, kadosh, so clearly you can't have חרטה
charatah and התרת נדרים, hataras nidarim, which is all braced on the
based on the idea that we're revealing that it's now in hindsight.
see you really didn't intend it. Okay, so if even an obvious
at the time error is still binding, clearly for בית שמאי Beis
Shammai there's no such thing as התרה hatara by הקדש. hekdesh.
Imagine a mystical magical element to it. Okay, yeah, independent of my
rational...
Exactly. The speech act is so powerful that it's not just an
expression of my thought as other types of speech acts are. Okay,
so now the Gemara says like this: דתנן בית שמאי אומרים אין
התרה בהקדש שנאמר בית שמאי אומרים הקדש טעות הקדש ובית הלל אומרים
אינו הקדש. De-tenan Beis Shammai omrim ein hatara behekdesh shenemar Beis Shammai
omrim hekdesh taus hekdesh uBeis Hillel omrim eino hekdesh. האי זה זה
מאי עביד ליה Hai zeh zeh mai avid lei? So what does
he do with the זה זה zeh zeh because he doesn't say
there's התרה hatara by הקדש? hekdesh? So it says, so מאי עביד
ליה? mai avid lei? זה דבר לשחוטי חוץ מיבעי ליה. Zeh davar
lishchutei chutz miba’ei lei. Fine, not for גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. Forget
גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. זה דבר לשחוטי חוץ Zeh davar lishchutei chutz
tells you something. על השוחט הוא חייב זה דבר. Al hashochait hu
chayav zeh davar. You're only חייב chayav if you שוחט shocht a
קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. על השוחט הוא חייב
ואינו חייב על המליק. Al hashochait hu chayav ve’eino chayav al hamalik.
Then if you do מליקה, melika, which is like the thing with
the fingernail on the back of the neck of the bird. So
even if you have a bird sacrifice, if you שוחט shocht it
outside the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you're חייב chayav for שחוטי חוץ.
shchutei chutz. If you do מליקה melika outside the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, you're not חייב. chayav. So it's telling you that's the...
בית שמאי Beis Shammai who holds there's no... בית הלל Beis Hillel
will still preserve the גזירה שוה, gezeira shava, right?
Is that it? Yeah. בית הלל Beis Hillel has a גזירה שוה,
gezeira shava, בית שמאי Beis Shammai forgets the גזירה שוה. gezeira shava.
זה Zeh is telling you something separate by each one. זה דבר
לראשי המטות מיבעי ליה. Zeh davar lerashei hamatos miba’ei lei. And what
does זה דבר zeh davar for ראשי המטות rashei hamatos tell you?
לחכם מתיר ואין בעל מתיר בעל מיפר ואין חכם מיפר. Lechacham matir
ve’ein baal matir baal meifer ve’ein chacham meifer. There's a difference between
התרה hatara and הפרה. hafara. Right? The husband hears it and if
ואם שמוע ישמע אישה ביום שמעו והניא את כל נדריה אשר עליה
ואת מבטא שפתיה. ve’im shamoa yishma isha beyom shamo veheini es kol
nedareha asher aleha ve’es mivta sefaseha. Does it say הפר hefer explicitly
by the husband or is that just a... what's the לשון? lashon?
Yeah.
כי הפר אותם ביום שמעו.
Ki hefer osam
beyom shamo. Okay, yeah. So it says הפר. hefer. So הפר hefer
is the לשון lashon in the פסוקים. pesukim. So what's the difference?
The husband has a power to annul, to... maybe annul is the
wrong word, to void. Okay, so he basically voids it. He hears
it on that day, he has 24 hours from the day he
hears it and he can void it. Okay, that's what the husband
does. The voiding works only from this point on. The נדר neder
was binding, the נדר neder was 100 percent. He just overrides and
voids it. So if the wife violated the נדר neder before he
voided it, she has violated it and she's liable for her violation.
Okay, that's what he does. So it's within 24 hours of hearing,
it's got that time limit and it's a power to void it.
Whereas the חכם chacham undoes it, is מתיר, matir, right? To release,
like you undo a knot, he undoes it. It never existed. We
now realize based on our conversation that you never... in that... it's
now clear that you never would have wanted to do it. It
was in error, so it never existed. So if you actually violated
it, now retroactively you didn't violate it. So that's the difference between
התרת נדרים hataras nedarim and הפרת נדרים. hafarat nedarim. And therefore, if
the חכם chacham uses the word of הפר, hefer, if rather than
saying הכל מותרים לך הכל מותרים לך, hakol mutarim lach hakol mutarim
lach, they say הכל מופרים לך, hakol mufarim lach, or מופר לך
מופר לך... mufar lach mufar lach... I know, but anyway, it doesn't
work. And if the husband says מותר לך מותר לך, mutar lach
mutar lach, it doesn't work. They're different modes and you have to
keep them distinct. Okay, so that's זה הדבר. zeh hadavar. Each one
has a distinct mode.
Okay, ולבית שמאי דלית להו גזירה שוה. uleBeis Shammai deleis lehu gezeira
shava. Now for בית שמאי Beis Shammai who doesn't hold the גזירה
שוה. gezeira shava. הפרת נדרים בשלשה הדיוטות מנא ליה Hafarat nedarim bishlosha
hedyotos mana lei? Right? That was the other thing the גזירה שוה
gezeira shava taught us. That התרת נדרים hataras nedarim doesn't only require
ראשי המטות. rashei hamatos. It could be even with שלשה הדיוטות, shlosha
hedyotos, right? Because אהרן ומשה וכל ישראל. Aharon uMoshe vechol Yisrael. So
where does בית שמאי Beis Shammai learn that from?
So נפקא ליה מדתניא nafka lei midetanya וידבר משה את מועדי ה'
אל בני ישראל. Vayedaber Moshe es moadei Hashem el bnei Yisrael. Okay,
this is in אמור Emor there.
So רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר. Rabbi Yossi HaGlili omer. Now it says
that at the end, right? It says אלה מועדי ה' אשר תקראו
אותם מקראי קודש אלה הם מועדי ששת ימים תעשה מלאכה. eileh moadei
Hashem asher tikre’u osam mikra’ei kodesh eileh heim moadai sheishes yamim te’aseh
melacha. Right, so it starts with שבת, Shabbos, it gives all the
מועדים moadim and then it says וידבר משה את מועדי ה' אל
בני ישראל. Vayedaber Moshe es moadei Hashem el bnei Yisrael. So what's
the repeating of it? So רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר מועדי ה' נאמרו.
Rabbi Yossi HaGlili omer moadei Hashem neemru. Only מועדי ה'. moadei Hashem.
שבת בראשית לא נאמרה. Shabbos Bereishis lo neemrah. Although שבת Shabbos is
mentioned at the beginning, אלה מועדי ה' ששת ימים, eileh moadei Hashem
sheishes yamim, when it says וידבר משה את מועדי ה' אל בני
ישראל, Vayedaber Moshe es moadei Hashem el bnei Yisrael, that last פסוק,
pasuk, only the מועדים, moadim, not שבת. Shabbos. Okay, בן עזאי אומר
מועדי ה' נאמרו. Ben Azzai omer moadei Hashem neemru. Only the מועדים
moadim he said to them. הפרת נדרים לא נאמרה. Hafarat nedarim lo
neemrah. Not הפרת נדרים. hafarat nedarim. So what the heck does this
mean? So the same way you don't know, רבי יוסי בר נתן
גמרא להא מתניתא. Rabbi Yossi bar Nasan gemara leha masnisa. He had
a tradition of this ברייתא, braisa, he was taught this
ברייתא. braisa. ולא ידעה לפרושה. Velo yadah lefarushah. He couldn't make any
sense of it. What's going on here? So he was so bothered,
אזל בתריה דרב ששת לנהרדעא. azal basrei deRav Sheshes liNarda’ah. He went
to find רב ששת, Rav Sheshes, he went all the way to
נהרדעא Narda’ah to explain to him what this ברייתא braisa means. ולא
אשכחיה. Velo ashkechei. He couldn't find him. אזל בתריה למחוזא. Azal basrei
leMechuza. So he'd already gone to מחוזא, Mechuza, so he went after
him to מחוזא. Mechuza. I told them, אמר ליה: Amar lei: מאי
מועדי ה' נאמרו שבת בראשית לא נאמרה? Mai Moadei Hashem ne'emru Shabbos
Bereishis lo ne'emra? What does that mean? It says, right, it says,
you know, the שבת Shabbos and anyway what’s it excluding שבת Shabbos
from? So אמר ליה, Amar lei, מועדי ה' צריכין קידוש בית דין,
Moadei Hashem tzerichin kiddush beis din, שבת בראשית אין צריכה קידוש בית
דין. Shabbos Bereishis ein tzericha kiddush beis din. The word אלה מועדי
ה' אשר תקראו אותם מקראי קודש, Eileh Moadei Hashem asher tikre'u osam
mikra'ei kodesh, you declare them holy days, right? So the מועדים moadim
only become the מועדים moadim if you declare them, if you make
ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. By making ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh that makes
the מועדים. moadim. Don't think just because שבת בראשית Shabbos Bereishis is
mentioned in the list of the מועדים moadim that that means that
שבת Shabbos doesn't have the קדושה kedusha of שבת Shabbos unless some
בית דין beis din comes along each week and declares it as
שבת. Shabbos. Apparently it is, I want to, I'll say something about
that. But although it says at the beginning אשר תקראו אותם מקראי
קודש, asher tikre'u osam mikra'ei kodesh, right? It is very funny to
say תקראו אותם מקראי קודש tikre'u osam mikra'ei kodesh and to start
with שבת. Shabbos. So what it's saying is no, שבת Shabbos has
obviously linked to the מועדים moadim but it doesn't require being declared
in order for it to have the קדושה kedusha of שבת. Shabbos.
Okay,
right, that's number one. Now, that's that דרשה. drasha.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka deitach amina, I would have thought, הוה וכתיב
בי גבי מועדות hava uchtiv bei gabei moados since it says by
the מועדות moados אשר תקראו אותם asher tikre'u osam תיבעי קידוש בית
דין כמועדות tiba'ei kiddush beis din kemoados קמשמע לן kamashma lan to
tell you no. At the end וידבר משה את מועדי ה', Vayedaber
Moshe es moadei Hashem, only מועדי ה' moadei Hashem are, you know,
are distinct from שבת. Shabbos. They don't require being declared. מאי מועדי
ה' נאמרו הפרת נדרים לא נאמרה? Mai Moadei Hashem ne'emru hafaras nedarim
lo ne'emra? What does this mean here about only מועדי ה' moadei
Hashem and not הפרת נדרים? hafaras nedarim? מועדי ה' צריכין מומחין. Moadei
Hashem tzerichin mumchin. You've for the מועדי ה' אשר תקראו אותם Moadei
Hashem asher tikre'u osam you need to be like you and אהרן.
Aharon. You need to be מומחין, mumchin, you need to be like
a בית דין beis din of experts, okay, not a יחיד מומחה.
yachid mumche. For קידוש החודש Kiddush Hachodesh you need a בית דין
beis din of מומחין mumchin like you and
אהרן. Aharon. הפרת נדרים לא נאמרה Hafaras nedarim lo ne'emra מומחין. mumchin.
הפרת נדרים אינה צריכה מומחין, Hafaras nedarim einah tzerichah mumchin, does not.
והראשי מטות כתיב, Veharashei matos kesiv, well what do you mean? It
says ראשי המטות. rashei hamatos. אמר רב חסדא אמר רבי יוחנן ביחיד
מומחה. Amar Rav Chisda amar Rabbi Yochanan beyachid mumche. That's what we
quoted earlier. ראשי המטות rashei hamatos is to tell you a מומחה
mumche has weight if you want to do an individual one, a
single יחיד yachid who's a מומחה mumche he can do הפרת נדרים.
hafaras nedarim. But you don't need a מומחה. mumche.
I said ראשי המטות, rashei hamatos, how do you get יחיד מומחה?
yachid mumche? So any other ראשי המטות rashei hamatos can do it
individually. I don't know what to say. Anyway, but if you want
to but it can also be done without מומחה mumche and then
that way it's distinguished from the פרשה parsha of מועדים. moadim. I
still don't get how we read הפרת נדרים hafaras nedarim into it
in order to distinguish it, but nevertheless that's the דרשה. drasha. This
requires a בית דין beis din of מומחין mumchin to do קידוש
החודש, kiddush hachodesh, there are other things that do not require it.
I'll just say one last thing about שבת בראשית אינה צריכה קידוש.
Shabbos Bereishis einah tzerichah kiddush. You know we make קידוש kiddush on
שבת, Shabbos, right? So the קידוש kiddush is like זכור את יום
השבת לקדשו, Zachor es yom haShabbos lekadesho, like we're remembering, we're declaring.
But Rav Soloveitchik in particular wrote, you know, has a couple of
pieces where he basically said that the that he wants to see
that the קידוש kiddush that we make adds a level of human
sanctity. שבת Shabbos doesn't need קדושה, kedusha, right? Without obviously it'll be
שבת Shabbos whether or not we make קידוש kiddush or not. But
when the making of קידוש, kiddush, you know, and you sort of
see this in the concept of like תוספת שבת tosefos Shabbos that
we can begin שבת Shabbos earlier, right? The making of קידוש kiddush
adds a level of human sanctity to something that's already קדוש, kadosh,
you know, from heaven. Whereas the מועדים, moadim, it's like the ברכה
bracha we make is מקדש ישראל והזמנים. Mekadesh Yisrael vehazmanim. It only
exists because of our sanctifying the ראשי חדשים. Roshei Chodashim. שבת Shabbos
exists without that, but that there also can be on top of
it another level of קדושה kedusha that we make through making קידוש.
kiddush. Okay, we will end with this.